## Angela Hood, Ph.D., LMFT, TTS, CTTP, CGCS, S.A.P.

4748 W. Atlantic BLVD #101 Margate, FL 33063 (754) 308-4818

Ahood7801@gmail.com

Experienced and qualified Clinical Director with experience in organizing and overseeing individuals and clinical programs. Utilize my leadership skills in supervising and directing clinical staff.

### **EXECUTIVE SUMMARY OF SKILLS & TRAINING:**

- Experience as adjunct professor, teaching courses on counseling and therapy at undergraduate and graduate level.
- Knowledge of human services outcomes and performance, learning and
- motivation, psychological research methods, and experience in the assessment and treatment of behavioral and affective disorders.
- Knowledge and experience in principles, methods, and procedures for diagnosis, treatment, and rehabilitation of physical and mental dysfunctions
- Proficient skills in selecting and using training/instructional methods and procedures appropriate for the situation when learning or teaching new things
- Proficient skills in performance assessments to make improvements or take corrective action.
- Therapist and Behavioral Health Clinician (BHC) with community mental health participants involved with DCF, Substance Abuse, and Dual Diagnosis
- Licensed Marriage and Family Therapist (LMFT), # MT3424
- Florida state Qualified Supervisor LMFT and LMHC
- Certified D.O.T.'s Substance Abuse Professional S.A.P.
- Association of Marriage and Family Therapist (AAMFT)
- Supervisor trained in Tapping for Trauma.
- Trained and experienced in Substance Abuse and Mental Health Assessments:
- Certified Tobacco Treatment Specialist,
- Certified Trauma Treatment Specialist.
- Trained and experienced in Solution-Focused Brief Therapy (SFBT),
- Narrative Therapy, Collaborative Therapy, and Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT)

### **EDUCATION**

**Ph.D., Marriage & Family Therapy, Degree confirmed** 2018 – Nova Southeastern University, Fort Lauderdale

Dissertation: The Experience of Sexual Abuse of Afro Caribbean Women: The Interpretive Phenomenological Analysis of the Particularities Attached to Disclosure

M.S., Marriage & Family Therapy, 2015 – Nova Southeastern University, Fort Lauderdale B.S., Psychology, 2012 – University of Phoenix, Tempe, Arizona

#### **LICENSE**

MT3424 - unrestricted effective 11/2017 expires 03/2023

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# **Smith Community Mental Health**

#### **Clinical Director**

- Assume responsibility of charts and EMR (eCR) auditing and compliance
- Sign and validate charts
- Assign primary therapist to incoming clients
- Review and approve discharge summaries
- Review and approve treatment plans
- Ensure clinicians are meeting required Medicaid guidelines
- Ensure department is staffed with qualified personnel when necessary
- Manage Timecards
- Complete annual reviews
- Conduct individual and group supervision
- Provide clinicians with clinical training and opportunities for continuous development
- Evaluate performance and discipline employees, when necessary.
- Monitor compliance to legal guidelines, internal policies and quality standards, as well and governing bodies
- Write and review policy and procedures
- Review and approve biopsychosocial
- Complete monthly and quarterly reports
- Participate in staff and leadership meetings

# Victory Recovery Center- Tamarac 07/2021-02/2022

### **Clinical Director**

- Assume responsibility of charts and EMR (KIPU) auditing and compliance
- Sign and validate charts
- Assign primary therapist to incoming clients
- Complete discharge summaries, ASAMS, continuing care, BCSC, AWARE, and PACS assessments
- Complete group schedule
- Ensure clinicians are completing forms according to 65D-30 guidelines
- Ensure department is staffed with qualified personnel when necessary
- Assign cases and create treatment plans for all patients
- Manage Timecards on Playflex
- Conduct weekly group supervision
- Conduct daily multidisciplinary meetings
- Complete letter of necessity to insurance companies
- Provide clinicians with clinical training and opportunities for continuous development

- Evaluate performance and discipline employees, when necessary.
- Monitor compliance to legal guidelines, internal policies and quality standards, as well and governing bodies
- Ensure clinical department adhere to 65-D-30 Rules
- Assist with completing master treatment plan and biopsychosocial

## We Level Up Mental Health Facility- Tamarac, Florida Assistant Clinical Director

- Oversight of master's level Primary Therapists, Case Manager, and bachelor's level Group Facilitators.
- Coordinates therapeutic care
- Audit chart
- Ensures the safe and appropriate clinical treatment of our clients
- Develop and oversee group schedules
- Assist in the coordination of aftercare and discharge planning
- Conduct daily staff meetings
- Provides weekly supervision for clinicians
- Maintain program census and KPI reports
- Management of my clinical team and daily clinical operations
- Assists in hiring and training new staff (clinical, case managers and BHT/MHT)
- Staff cases with clinicians and provides guidance on recommendations and disposition
- Maintain staff schedule
- Assists director with policy and procedure creation and maintenance
- Works with the Executive Director to ensure that programs are regularly evaluated for best practice standards and modifications made when necessary
- Mitigate crisis and conduct Baker Acts
- Assist Operations Manager when needed

# Broward Addiction & Recovery Center (BARC), Fort Lauderdale, Florida Lead Behavioral Health Clinician (BHC), 02/2019 to 06/2021

- Work collaboratively with staff to increase efficiencies, decrease costs, reduce variability, reduce errors/defects, and involve all appropriate personnel
- Complete suicide assessments (SAAP), Initial Clinical Screening (ICS), Mimi Mental Health Assessment (MMS), American Society of Addiction Medicine (ASAM) assessments, and Biopsychosocial Assessment (BPS) to evaluate substance abuse, mental health, and co-occurring disorders
- Utilize Motivational Interview skills and Solution Focus to extrapolate information from the client regarding their substance abuse history and preferred future.
- Oversee department activities and provide case consultation in difficult cases.
- Provides back-up case management and/or counseling in absence of assigned staff member; reviews case records to evaluate the quality of work and to ensure compliance with procedures and requirements.
- Assist with Baker Acts

- Conduct weekly peer reviews.
- Assist with staff meetings as needed.
- Complete clinical assessment for clients Marchman Act to detox or court ordered.
- Monitors clinical records for quality of work and to ensure compliance with agency and funder requirements or standards.
- Review clinical assessments.
- Assist with and conduct AMA interventions.
- Assists staff with crisis intervention services for high-risk consumers.
- Conduct weekly psychoeducational substances abuse groups and smoking cessation groups.
- Supervise clinical interns and staff as needed.
- Run daily detox client reports.
- Participate in nursing shift change report.
- Assign residential beds.
- Develop individualized treatment plans in partnership with clients, using research-based addiction therapy.
- Ensure discharge summaries and transfer summaries are accurate and complete.
- Partner with client's family and loved ones throughout the rehabilitation process when possible.
- Work with clients to develop comprehensive discharge/aftercare plans.
- Maintain progress notes and clinical documentation in EDCO Health Information Solutions software.
- Demonstrates excellent customer service skills while interacting with the clients and staff.
- Assist with procedure development and prepare project reports and related data.
- Provide advanced services for the Detox department, assisting other therapists, maintaining the smooth functioning of the department.

# Thrive Therapy Institute, Fort Lauderdale, Florida Clinical Director, 2017 to 04/22

- Provide crisis intervention, case supervision, and evaluations. Coordinate and delegate cases and staff coverage, review clinical documentation
- Implement quality initiatives for performance improvement in the organization
- Utilize process flow and group management techniques to support individuals and teams through improvement initiatives
- Assist clients, using various modalities and appropriate intervention, to develop healthy coping skills, strengthen drug refusal skills, and manage anxiety
- Utilize appropriate and acceptable judgment, clinical theories, and professional knowledge
  of methods and ethics to restore or enhance social, psychosocial, or biopsychosocial
  functioning
- Oversee the daily tasks of staff, supervise interns, conduct performance evaluations

# Touro University, Worldwide Adjunct Professor

- Teach specific subject topics to PhD and DMFT Students
- Collaborate in developing online weekly lecture through blackboard.
- Collaborate in developing weekly lecture for classroom discussion.
- Facilitate students meeting course objectives by providing appropriate learning experiences.
- Evaluate students 'achievement of curricular objective outcomes.
- Advance student learning through dedicated instruction in accordance with courts outline
- Conduct weekly discussion with Department Chair and Lead Professor
- Internal practicum supervisor

•

# South Florida Bible College & Theological Seminary, Deerfield Beach, Florida Adjunct Professor, 2018 to present

- Instruction, course preparation, development of syllabus and instructional materials, grading and assessment (using Populi software)
- Teach undergraduate and Master level courses: Assessments, Counseling skills, and Counseling Children, Pastoral Counseling, supervise students Practicum
- Provide appropriate learning experiences to facilitate students meeting course objectives

# Counseling Mediation Education and Treatment (CMET), Fort Lauderdale, Florida Lead Therapist, 2016-2017

- Conducted Initial Clinical Screening (ICS) and Biopsychosocial Assessment (BPS), conducted clinical intake and assessments, developed treatment plans with program participants.
- Supervise clinical staff as needed.
- Conducted case management, case consultation, and provided individual, family, counseling.
- Conducted parenting, anger management, substance abuse, life skills and domestic violence groups.
- Conducted 1:1 Parenting Observation and APPI-1 pre and APPI-2 Post-parenting Assessments.
- Develop individualized treatment plans in partnership with clients, using research-based addiction therapy.
- Monitors clinical records for quality of work and to ensure compliance with agency and funder requirements or standards.
- Participate in staff meetings, trainings and developments.
- Conduct crisis interventions
- Maintained clinical records electronically using Lauris. Prepared monthly reports to ChildNet
- Evaluated individual and family functioning within work, family, and routines of daily living and identified areas needing continued support, resources, and treatment to assist clients.
- Supervise and train interns.

### The Enrichment Center, Fort Lauderdale, Florida

## Lead Christian Counselor, 2001-present

- Provide Christian counseling to children, families, couples, and individuals using biblical principles, develop individual treatment plans, conduct reviews of treatment plans
- Implement quality initiatives for performance improvement in the organization
- Utilize process flow and group management techniques to support individuals and teams through improvement initiatives
- Utilize strong interpersonal and communication skills to communicate succinctly and effectively across all levels of the organization
- Train ministers in Christian counseling, mentor apprentice leaders, and develop discipleship training. Train ministers on respect for diversity and culture.
- Supervise current leadership staff and oversee daily operation of ministry. Oversee program budget, report, and data collection using Power Church Plus software.

## PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Participate in monthly mental health awareness and substance abuse prevention focus groups with United Way of Broward County
- Attended Solution Focus Brief Therapy: Theory Practice by Dr. Gordon Nova University 05/2014
- Attended Relations Suicide Assessment: Risks, Resources, and Possibilities for Safety by Dr. Flemons at Nova University 10/2013
- Attended The Impact of Trauma and Substance Abuse on Eating Disorders Hosted by Mental Health Association 05/16/2014
- Attended Conference on Professional Excellence hosted by Broward Coalition on Aging (BCOA) and the Mental Health Association on 04/25/2014
- Attended Supervision and Training with MFT Micro-skills by Dr. Schooley Nova University 06/07/2014
- Attended Intensive Solution Focused Conference hosted by Connie Elliot 05/2014
- Attended and completed abuse, neglect and abandonment/mandatory reporting 07/2015
- Attend and complete Florida State Family Mediation 07/2016
- Attend and Completed Collaborative Training Groups SBIRT Assessment Training 10/25/2017
- Attend and completed FSU tobacco specialist certification training 06/2019
- Attend and complete Trauma Certified Training 04/2019

### **PROFESSIONAL PRESENTATIONS**

- Fall Term, 10/2013, Guest Lecturer at Nova Southeastern University, CAHSS Human Development Course Topic: Christianity and Sexuality
- Fall Term, 10/2014 Guest Lecturer at Nova Southeastern University, CAHSS Human Development Course Topic: Christianity and Sexuality
- Fall Term, 10/2015 Guest Lecturer at Nova Southeastern University, CAHSS Human Development Course Topic: Christianity and Sexuality

- Presented at United Way of Broward County's Commission on Substance Abuse National Behavioral Health conference 05/2017; Theme of presentation: Using Systemic Principles for Preventing Burnout & Increasing Resiliency
- Fall Term, 10/2017 Guest Lecturer at Nova Southeastern University, CAHSS Ethics Course Topic: Mediation Ethics
- Fall Term, 11/2017 Guest Lecturer at Broward Collage, General Psychology Course Topic: Stress Management
- Winter Term, 03/2018 Guest Lecturer at Nova Southeastern University, CAHSS Human Development Course Topic: Sex and Christianity: Considering Religious Views when working With African Americans
- Presented at United Way of Broward County's Commission on Substance Abuse National Behavioral Health conference 05/2018; Theme of presentation: Using Systemic Principles to Increase Resiliency in Afro-Caribbean women Who Experienced Trauma
- Summer Term, 03/2018 Guest Lecturer at Nova Southeastern University, CAHSS Human Development Course Topic: Private Practice: How to start a private practice.
- Guest Lecture 02/2021- at Nova Southeastern University, CAHSS Human Development Course Topic Couples Counseling and Private Practice
- Guest Lecture 03/2021- at Nova Southeastern University, CAHSS Human Development Course Topic ......

## **RESEARCH WORK**

**08/2017-05/2018** Research Assistant with Dr. Ron Chaniel – Healthy Mothers, Healthy Babies Coalition of Broward County, Inc. using a mixed-methods design to assess how effective the Healthy Mothers, Healthy Babies Coalition of Broward County's Fatherhood Mentorship Program meets its objectives and goals to help men develop the skills needed to become and remain active in their children's life.

07/2017 – 12/2019 Dissertation Research- The Experience of Sexual Abuse of Afro Caribbean Women: The Interpretive Phenomenological Analysis of The Particularities Attached to Disclosure

### PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

- Certified Substance Abuse Professional (S.A.P.)
- Certified Trauma Counselor (CCTP)
- Certified Tobacco Specialist (TTP)
- Certified Grief Counseling Specialist (CGCS)
- AAMFT Approved Supervisor
- Qualified State Supervisor (Florida)
- Supervisory or management experience
- Excellent Interpersonal skills and boundaries
- Excellent time management skills
- 20 years 'experience in human development and outreach services in a community-based organization
- 17 years of coaching and teaching experience

- Experienced in organizational and project management.
- Ability to manage multiple projects.
- Demonstrates clear verbal and written communication.
- Work independently and collaboratively and strong interpersonal skills.
- Knowledge of HIPPA, confidentiality and privacy practices
- Knowledgeable in Postmodern therapies: Solution Focused, Narrative Therapy and Collaborative Therapy
- Knowledgeable in CBT and motivational interviewing
- Knowledge, education, training, skills, and experience in a multi-disciplinary approach to physical and mental health.
- Excellent communication skills including diplomacy, tact, and effective bedside manner with patients.
- Ability to display non-judgmental attitude
- Knowledge of DSM-IV TR and DSM 5 diagnoses and symptoms
- Skilled at assessing level of suicidality in individuals who present for help
- Ability to maintain composure, professionalism, and structure in any given situation
- Ability to handle and resolve recurring problems

### **PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS and PUBLICATIONS**

- AAMFT Association of Marriage and Family Therapist
- AACC American Association of Christian Counseling
- Tri-One Vice-Chair
- Hood, A. & Cayo, D. (2013). Family Secrets
- Hood, A (2019) Unlocking the Keys to God's Promises
- Hood, A. (2019). You Have Authority from God, Now What!
- Hood, Angela (2009). It's Your Life Take Authority
- Jim Hibel, Jim Duvall, Nika Alakbarova, Alexandra Gard, Angela Hood, Clint Lambert, Claire Loucka, Michaelle Pierre, Arthrine Roberts, Katia Tikhonravova, (2016). Valuing our values: Short stories of revitalizing traditional work contexts by reclaiming collaborative practices. Nova Southeastern University & JST INSTITUTE
- In Progress-Hood, Angela & Gomes, Ronnie (2019). Religious and Spiritual Consultation: How do conduct Christian consultation when working with clients in therapy.
- In Progress- Group commiseration on disenfranchised grief: Submitted a chapter, Sexual Abuse and Disenfranchised Grief, written by educators at Nova Southeastern University.
- In progress-Hood, A,. & Burnett, C. (2019) Bullied Into Silence. (chronicling how victims of sexual assault are often silenced by family or society and how they can be given a voice).

### PROFESSIONAL LICENSES AND REGISTRATION

- Licensed Marriage and Family Therapist MT3424
- Trained Florida Supreme Court Certified Family Mediator
- Trained Florida Certified Parent Coordinator

### TRAINING AND CERTIFICATION

- 2008 HIV 500/501 State of Florida HIV testing, counseling training course
- 2009 Outstanding Volunteer Services United Way of Broward County
- 2006 Certified Child Care Provider by DCF
- 2004 Business Development
- 2005 Notary Public Seal (Current)
- 2000 Organization and Leadership Staff Development
- 2000 Managing Conflict- Training
- 2009 Hopes Women's Center Youth Prevention Diploma
- 2015 PREPARE/ENRICH Certified Facilitator
- 2016 State of Florida Family Mediator
- 2017 Child Abuse and Neglect Training
- 2018 Qualified State Supervisor-
- 2019 Certified Trauma Professional
- 2019 Certified Tobacco Treatment Specialist

### **REFERENCE**

•	Tonita Gregory	Accounting Director	(954) 632-2230
•	Dr. Lamor Ast	Professor/mentor	(305) 724-8861
•	Dr. Charmaine Borda	Clinical supervisor	(954) 701-0241
•	Dr. Jacqueline Clarke	Family Therapist	(954) 274-0507